<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Dashboard Dude]]></title>
  <link href="http://dashboarddude.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://dashboarddude.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-11-09T17:44:37-03:00</updated>
  <id>http://dashboarddude.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rowan]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dashboard: Tasseo]]></title>
    <link href="http://dashboarddude.com/blog/2013/11/09/dashboard-tasseo/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-09T18:00:00-03:00</updated>
    <id>http://dashboarddude.com/blog/2013/11/09/dashboard-tasseo</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So I lied. The first of my series of <a href="http://dashboarddude.com/blog/2013/09/09/dashboard-reviews/">dashboard reviews</a> is NOT on Dusk, but one of
Obfuscurity&#8217;s other great dashboards: <a href="https://github.com/obfuscurity/tasseo">Tasseo</a>.</p>

<h2>Tasseo</h2>

<p><a href="https://github.com/obfuscurity/tasseo">Tasseo</a> is a small, lightweight dashboard that&#8217;s good for throwing together a
useful monitoring dashboard in a minimal amount of time. It&#8217;s built with
<a href="http://code.shutterstock.com/rickshaw/">Rickshaw</a> graphs (themselves based on
the fantastic JavaScript library <a href="http://d3js.org/">D3.js</a>) on top of a small
<a href="http://www.sinatrarb.com/">Sinatra</a> application.</p>

<p><img src="https://github.com/obfuscurity/tasseo/raw/master/lib/tasseo/public/i/tasseo.png" title="Tasseo Dashboard" alt="graph" /></p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Features</h3>

<ul>
<li>Configuration for dashboards is done with simple JavaScript Objects.</li>
<li>You can set value thresholds for changing the colour of a graph from green
(default), yellow (warning), and red (critical).</li>
</ul>


<h3>Good For</h3>

<ul>
<li><strong>Getting up and running quickly.</strong> There&#8217;s just enough configuration options,
but not too many. This can get you from the default Graphite dashboards (which
can be a bit hard on the eye) to a nice looking monitoring dashboard in minutes,
not hours.</li>
<li><strong>Showing specific, discrete metrics</strong> for a high-level operations dashboard.</li>
<li>Metrics you want to set visual thresholds for.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Not so Good For</h3>

<ul>
<li><strong>Displaying large numbers of metrics.</strong> The layout eats in to your total
space (if you want to display lots of similar metrics, look at horizon charts
like Dusk instead).</li>
<li><strong>Discovering new important metrics.</strong> Mainly because it doesn&#8217;t show a large
number of metrics, you&#8217;re unlikely to find out new key metrics while using
Tasseo.</li>
<li><strong>Viewing metrics in detail over time.</strong> There&#8217;s no rulers showing you what
the values in the chart represent, so it can be hard to know what the exact
values were in the past. The current value is displayed numerically, so it&#8217;s not
an issue if you&#8217;re only interested in historical trends - not values.</li>
<li><strong>Zooming/investigating metrics on the dashboard.</strong> What you see is what you
get, but it&#8217;s enough for a high-level monitoring dashboard.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Links</h3>

<p>Check it out on <a href="https://github.com/obfuscurity/tasseo">GitHub</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dashboard Reviews]]></title>
    <link href="http://dashboarddude.com/blog/2013/09/09/dashboard-reviews/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-09T10:00:00-03:00</updated>
    <id>http://dashboarddude.com/blog/2013/09/09/dashboard-reviews</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In this new series of posts I will be reviewing (in detail) some of the more
popular real-time dashboards out there. Don&#8217;t forget to sign up to the mailing
list <strong>on the right</strong> to get the reviews as they come out.</p>

<p>Most of the posts will focus on front-end dashboards for Graphite, but if there
are any other types of dashboards you think would be good to review just <a href="mailto:rowan@dashboarddude.com">send me an email</a>.
I will be doing a review of <a href="http://shopify.github.io/dashing/">Shopify&#8217;s Dashing</a>, because it&#8217;s one of my favourites.</p>

<p>The first review (coming soon) will be on on <a href="http://obfuscurity.com/">Obfuscurity&#8217;s</a>
newest dashboard: <a href="https://github.com/obfuscurity/dusk">Dusk</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dashing Dashboard Widget Challenge: The Hotness]]></title>
    <link href="http://dashboarddude.com/blog/2013/08/16/dashing-dashboard-widget-challenge-the-hotness/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-16T14:49:00-03:00</updated>
    <id>http://dashboarddude.com/blog/2013/08/16/dashing-dashboard-widget-challenge-the-hotness</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="http://dashboarddude.com/images/posts/dashing-hotness-widget/hot.png" width="250" height="250" title="Hot hot hot!" ></p>

<p>The friendly <a href="https://twitter.com/davefp">David from Shopify</a> contacted me
recently about the <a href="http://dashing.challengepost.com/">Shopify Widget Challenge</a> that they&#8217;re holding. I&#8217;ve
written about <a href="http://dashboarddude.com/blog/2013/01/23/dashboards-for-graphite">Dashing before</a>, and
I&#8217;m a big fan of its style and versatility.</p>

<p>It didn&#8217;t take me long to think of some widget ideas, so I thought I&#8217;d share
what it took for me to enter the challenge with a basic idea.</p>

<p>You can see the resulting widget <a href="https://gist.github.com/rowanu/6246149">in this
gist</a>.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>My Idea</h2>

<p>The idea I had was for a widget that changed colour, depending on the value it
is displaying - kind of like the Meter and Number Widgets that comes with
Dashing, but <strong>hotter</strong>.</p>

<p>My plan is for this to be a big, bold, colourful way of
drawing focus to metrics which need immediate attention (because something&#8217;s
about to explode, etc).</p>

<p>It&#8217;s worth noting that the Number widget actually has (undocumented?) &#8216;warning&#8217;
and &#8216;danger&#8217; values that can be set (which cause the widget to pulse), but these
require a status to be set on the data sent to the widget (from the job). I
wanted something that would &#8216;just work&#8217; with numerical data, as it&#8217;s a common
use-case I see.</p>

<h2>The Dashing Dashboard</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://shopify.github.io/dashing/">Dashing page</a> has the basic information
you need to create your own widget:</p>

<blockquote><p>Anatomy of a widget</p>

<p>an HTML file used for layout and bindings</p>

<p>a SCSS file for styles</p>

<p>a coffeescript file which allows you to handle incoming data &amp; functionality</p></blockquote>

<p>That combined with the <a href="https://github.com/Shopify/dashing/tree/master/templates/project/widgets">existing examples</a>
and the <a href="https://github.com/Shopify/dashing/wiki/Additional-Widgets">3rd party widgets</a> as
reference points means that there are plenty examples out there to learn from.</p>

<h2>My Widget</h2>

<h3>HTML Template</h3>

<p>The template I decided was appropriate was super-simple - this widget is really
only trying to convey a single value, so I based it off the &#8216;vanilla&#8217; Number
Widget.</p>

<pre><code>&lt;h1 class="title" data-bind="title"&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 class="value" data-bind="value | shortenedNumber | prepend prefix | append suffix"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class="updated-at" data-bind="updatedAtMessage"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>This just shows the title (if present), value (in a shortened format, with
prefix and suffixes - if present), and finally a small &#8216;updated at&#8217; message (as
most widgets in Dashing do).</p>

<h2>Styling with SASS</h2>

<p><img class="left" src="http://dashboarddude.com/images/posts/dashing-hotness-widget/cool.png" width="250" height="250" title="Everything's cool" ></p>

<p>Dashing comes with <a href="http://sass-lang.com/">SASS</a> support, which is another nice
touch by the developers.</p>

<p>I had originally hoped to auto-generate the colour spectrum for the widget
using some of SASS&#8217; <a href="http://nex-3.com/posts/89-powerful-color-manipulation-with-sass">advanced colour methods</a>, but
in the end I decided to keep it simple for this first version, and use a
palette created by <a href="http://www.colourlovers.com/lover/nekoyo">Nekyo</a> called
<a href="http://www.colourlovers.com/palette/56122/Sweet_Lolly">Sweet Lolly</a>. I found
this through the <a href="http://www.colourlovers.com/">COLOURlovers</a> site, and grabbed
it because I really wanted something that went from green to red, with yellow
in the middle.</p>

<h3>CSS3 Transitions</h3>

<p>After reading this <a href="http://css3.bradshawenterprises.com/transitions/">great description of CSS3 transitions</a>, I created the
required SCSS for my widget. In order to make the code a little more readable,
I included a
<a href="http://sass-lang.com/docs/yardoc/file.SASS_REFERENCE.html#mixins">mixin</a> to
handle all the browser-specific directives:</p>

<pre><code>@mixin transition($transition-property, $transition-time, $method) {
  -webkit-transition: $transition-property $transition-time $method;
  -moz-transition: $transition-property $transition-time $method;
  -o-transition: $transition-property $transition-time $method;
  transition: $transition-property $transition-time $method;
}
</code></pre>

<p>Which meant that when I wanted to transition the background-color for my
widget, all I need to include in the SCSS is:</p>

<pre><code>@include transition(background-color, 1s, linear);
</code></pre>

<p>This might be a bit of overkill for the one usage, originally considered
some other transitions (and may still include them in a future version), so I
&#8216;did it right&#8217; the first time.</p>

<h3>CoffeeScript Functionality</h3>

<p><img class="right" src="http://dashboarddude.com/images/posts/dashing-hotness-widget/neutral.png" width="250" height="250"></p>

<p>The widget functionality resides in a CoffeeScript/JavaScript file, which will
be included by Dashing at runtime. All of the included widgets are written in
CoffeeScript, so I wanted to keep consistent with that. I&#8217;m also a big fan of
CoffeeScript - I find it a bit more maintainable than JavaScript, especially for
small files like this.</p>

<h4>The onData Event</h4>

<p>In my basic widget, all of the magic happens in the <code>onData</code> event, which all widgets
receive when (surprise surprise!) data is sent to them by the scheduled jobs.</p>

<p>All I needed to do was change (toggle) the background colour (using CSS) of the
widget to represent its place between two user supplied values: &#8216;warm&#8217; and
&#8216;cool&#8217;. Anything outside those values will be shown as &#8216;hot&#8217; and &#8216;cold&#8217;
respectively (ie. the max and min colour values). Anything inside those values
will use an interpolated value from three possible choices (cool, neutral, and
warm).</p>

<p>There&#8217;s also a <code>ready</code> event, which fires when the widget is first loaded (ie.
when the page is loaded). This could be useful to configure the widget in a
certain way, depending on user settings, etc.</p>

<p>Here&#8217;s the <code>onData</code> listener that makes the widget work (in CoffeeScript):</p>

<pre><code>onData: (data) -&gt;
  node = $(@node)
  value = parseInt data.value
  cool = parseInt node.data "cool"
  warm = parseInt node.data "warm"
  level = switch
    when value &lt;= cool then 0
    when value &gt;= warm then 4
    else 
      bucketSize = (warm - cool) / 3 # Total # of colours in middle
      Math.ceil (value - cool) / bucketSize
</code></pre>

<p>It could&#8217;ve easily been shortened to a few lines, but I like taking a few extra
to make it nice and readable.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>Hopefully this will help you create your own widgets for Shopify&#8217;s Dashing
Dashboard. You can see (and install) the widget yourself by checking out <a href="https://gist.github.com/rowanu/6246149">the
gist</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Kudos to the Shopify guys</strong> for making a cool piece of software, and making it
so easy to extend!</p>

<p>If you&#8217;ve got a good idea for a widget (and it&#8217;s not after September 13th,
2013), you should enter the <a href="http://dashing.challengepost.com/">Shopify Widget Challenge</a>!</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://dashboarddude.com/images/posts/dashing-hotness-widget/cold.png" width="250" height="250" title="Green is good" ></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Installing Graphite with Ceres Awesomeness]]></title>
    <link href="http://dashboarddude.com/blog/2013/04/30/installing-graphite-with-ceres-awesomeness/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-30T15:37:00-03:00</updated>
    <id>http://dashboarddude.com/blog/2013/04/30/installing-graphite-with-ceres-awesomeness</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The Dashboard Dude is still here, he&#8217;s just busy with Real Life™
unfortunately&#8230;</p>

<p>While I work on my next post, here are links to some others I did at my last
workplace about getting started with Graphite, including using the new back-end
replacement for Whisper - Ceres.</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://blog.sweetiq.com/2013/01/getting-started-with-graphite/">Getting started with Graphite</a></li>
<li><a href="http://blog.sweetiq.com/2013/01/using-ceres-as-the-back-end-database-to-graphite/">Setting up Ceres as the back end database to Graphite</a></li>
<li><a href="http://blog.sweetiq.com/2013/01/carbon-daemon-writer-setup-in-megacarbon/">Setting up the new carbon-daemon for writing metrics in Graphite</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dashboards for Graphite]]></title>
    <link href="http://dashboarddude.com/blog/2013/01/23/dashboards-for-graphite/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-23T08:17:00-03:00</updated>
    <id>http://dashboarddude.com/blog/2013/01/23/dashboards-for-graphite</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&#8217;s no secret I like <a href="http://graphite.wikidot.com/">Graphite</a> - it&#8217;s a great example of Open Source software
which is just as good (actually, it&#8217;s even better) than similar closed-source,
enterprise-grade (and much more <strong>expensive</strong>) software.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://dashboarddude.com/images/posts/dashboards-for-graphite/boring.png" width="400" height="300" title="A bit dull..." ></p>

<p>While Graphite is fantastic, the front-end that comes with it leaves a little
bit to be desired. You <em>can</em> use the built-in rendering and dashboard for viewing
your system metrics, just like you <em>can</em> use Internet Explorer 6 to browse the
Internet - it&#8217;ll work, but <a href="http://www.quickmeme.com/meme/3osf83/">you&#8217;re gonna have a bad time</a>.</p>

<p>Thankfully, there are a lot of alternatives out there, but the <a href="http://graphite.readthedocs.org/en/latest/tools.html">Graphite Tools</a>
page is a little out of date (with abandoned/incomplete projects), <strong>so here&#8217;s a
list or dashboards I have or would consider using&#8230;</strong></p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Client-side Dashboards</h2>

<p>These dashboards use the <a href="http://graphite.readthedocs.org/en/latest/render_api.html">Graphite Render API</a> to get data, and show them using
some of the latest client-side Javascript libraries (like <a href="http://d3js.org/">D3.js</a>) to render
graphs.</p>

<p>These dashboards usually <strong>perform noticeably better than the built-in renderer</strong>,
because it shifts the rendering work to your browser, rather than the server
(which is already working to retrieve the metrics from disk, etc).</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/kenhub/giraffe"><img class="right" src="http://dashboarddude.com/images/posts/dashboards-for-graphite/giraffe.png" width="150" height="300" title="Giraffe" ></a></p>

<h3><a href="https://github.com/kenhub/giraffe">Giraffe</a></h3>

<p>A <a href="http://code.shutterstock.com/rickshaw/">Rickshaw</a>-based (which is built on d3.js) dashboard with a nice interface for
toggling metrics and changing the time period being shown on the fly.</p>

<p>While I haven&#8217;t used it personally, it looks good. My only concern is the
performance, as even <a href="http://kenhub.github.com/giraffe/#dashboard=Demo&amp;timeFrame=1d">the small demo</a> is a bit slow.</p>

<h3><a href="http://square.github.com/cubism/">Cubism.js</a></h3>

<p><a href="http://square.github.com/cubism/"><img class="right" src="http://dashboarddude.com/images/posts/dashboards-for-graphite/cubism.js.png" width="400" height="300" title="Cubism.js" ></a>
This is a great dashboard for fitting a large number of metrics on one screen.
The horizon graph is suited to comparing many similar metrics, and the default
colour scheme is really easy on the eyes, without loosing detail.</p>

<p>While the current values are displayed, you&#8217;ll need to mouse-over the previous
updates which may not suit some dashboards.</p>

<p><a href="http://jondot.github.com/graphene/"><img class="right" src="http://dashboarddude.com/images/posts/dashboards-for-graphite/graphene.png" width="400" height="300" title="Graphene" ></a></p>

<h3><a href="http://jondot.github.com/graphene/">Graphene</a></h3>

<p>A good general-purpose replacement for your Graphite dashboards.
As you can see on its demo page, it has widgets for gauges and counters, if
you&#8217;re using <a href="https://github.com/etsy/statsd">StatsD&#8217;s</a> extra features.</p>

<p>It has a nice auto-discovery feature, which can convert your existing
Graphite dashboards to their Graphene equivalent quickly, but I find the
dark/high contrast/high intensity colour scheme tough to look at for long
periods of time (but that can be changed with some extra CSS styling).</p>

<h3><a href="https://github.com/obfuscurity/tasseo">Tasseo</a></h3>

<p><a href="https://github.com/obfuscurity/tasseo"><img class="right" src="http://dashboarddude.com/images/posts/dashboards-for-graphite/tasseo.png" width="400" height="300" title="Tasseo" ></a>
Another Rickshaw-based front-end, it&#8217;s a very light-weight dashboard for viewing
many different metrics (ie. they don&#8217;t have to be on the same scale) at once.</p>

<p>It Can be easily configured to change colour when certain thresholds are breached,
which makes it nice as a high-level dashboard. It&#8217;s not suited for long-term
metric monitoring, as there are no y-axes drawn which can make working out
historical values a bit hard.</p>

<p>This is a dashboard by Jason Dixon, who also does the Descartes dashboard (see below).</p>

<h2>Database-backed Dashboards</h2>

<p>These databases have more features than the client-side dashboards, but require
more set up and configuration to get running. Most reduce the load on your
Graphite server by caching often-used data (eg. by using <a href="http://redis.io/">Redis</a>).</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/paperlesspost/graphiti"><img class="right" src="http://dashboarddude.com/images/posts/dashboards-for-graphite/graphiti.jpeg" width="400" height="300" title="Graphiti" ></a></p>

<h3><a href="https://github.com/paperlesspost/graphiti">Graphiti</a></h3>

<p>A Redis-backed dashboard replacement which uses JSON to configure graphs. It
uses Redis as a metric and settings cache, and it has the ability to store
snapshots of your graphs on Amazon&#8217;s S3. One thing to note is that it
deliberately doesn&#8217;t do authentication - it makes the (not unreasonable)
assumption that your Graphite data and dashboards are not on a public network.</p>

<h3><a href="https://github.com/obfuscurity/descartes">Descartes</a></h3>

<p>Definitely the most comprehensive replacement for Graphite&#8217;s built-in dashboard
so far, which isn&#8217;t really surprising given it&#8217;s by Jason Dixon (see below).
It depends on Redis and PostreSQL, which also puts it at the top of the
requirements list.</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/obfuscurity/descartes"><img class="right" src="http://dashboarddude.com/images/posts/dashboards-for-graphite/descartes.png" width="400" height="200" title="Descartes" ></a>
It has the ability to set templates for graphs, and uses sparklines to give you
a high-level overview of your metrics and help you decide what you want to
include in your dashboard, which is always useful.</p>

<p>Authentication of users can be done with Goolge OpenID or Github, and comes
with great instructions on how to deploy to Heroku, which will help you get up
and running quickly.</p>

<p>While I haven&#8217;t had a chance to use Descartes myself, I would trust anything
that <a href="https://github.com/obfuscurity">Jason Dixon</a> puts out - he is one of the <a href="https://github.com/graphite-project?tab=members">Graphite Project</a> maintainers
and did the Tasseo dashboard (see above), so you know he knows his stuff.
His blog is full of useful <a href="http://obfuscurity.com/Tags/Graphite">Graphite tips</a>.</p>

<h2>Other Dashboards</h2>

<p>While not specifically Graphite dashboards, the following get an honourable
mention:</p>

<h3><a href="https://github.com/ripienaar/gdash">GDash</a></h3>

<p><a href="https://github.com/ripienaar/gdash"><img class="right" src="http://dashboarddude.com/images/posts/dashboards-for-graphite/gdash.png" width="200" height="100" title="GDash" ></a>
This dashboard is not client-side (it uses Graphite&#8217;s internal renderer for
images) or database backed, so it&#8217;s more of a &#8220;skin&#8221; on the default dashboard.
It lets you configure your dashboards using YAML, and is built on the Twitter
Bootstrap web-framework.</p>

<h3><a href="https://github.com/Dieterbe/graph-explorer">Graph Explorer</a></h3>

<p><a href="https://github.com/Dieterbe/graph-explorer"><img class="right" src="http://dashboarddude.com/images/posts/dashboards-for-graphite/explorer.png" width="300" height="150" title="Graph Explorer" ></a>
While this isn&#8217;t a dashboard (like the others in this list), it&#8217;s a new take on
metric exploration for Graphite. Made to be very interactive, it can definitely
help you decide what metrics to include in your dashboard. The nice thing is
that he graphs created are interactive, which is a big improvement over the
usual metric explorer built-in to Graphite.</p>

<h3><a href="http://shopify.github.com/dashing/">Dashing</a></h3>

<p><a href="http://shopify.github.com/dashing/"><img class="left" src="http://dashboarddude.com/images/posts/dashboards-for-graphite/dashing.png" width="200" height="200" title="Dashing" ></a>
A general-purpose dashboard by the boffins at <a href="http://www.shopify.com/">Shopify</a>, Dashing can accept data
from many different sources, and display many different types of data through
various widgets. This includes being able to display Graphite data through
direct calls to the Render URL API (you&#8217;ll have to roll them yourself), and
display them using their Rickshaw graph widget.</p>

<p>I&#8217;m a big fan or Dashing for non-technical dashboards because it can accept so
many types/sources of data, and looks great out of the box. They also have a
gauge widget which works really nicely with the StatsD&#8217;s gauge metrics.
The have a <a href="http://dashingdemo.herokuapp.com/sampletv">great demo of the various widgets in action</a>.</p>

<h2>Need Help?</h2>

<p>There you have it! Let me your personal experiences and recommendations with
these dashboards, or if I missed any you think are worthwhile in the comments below.</p>

<p>If you need any help setting up any of these dashboards, or Graphite itself,
check out <a href="http://dashboarddude.com/services">my dashboard consulting services</a> and <a href="http://dashboarddude.com/contact">get in touch with me</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
